is to find ways that you can promote and activate those stem cells in your brain already to react and respond appropriately to damage to repair it. That will be the future. There will be drugs that will do that. But the other way is to effectively parachute in cells, transplant them in, to replace dying or lost cells, even in the brain. And I want to tell you now an experiment, it's a clinical trial that we did, which recently completed, which is with colleagues in UCL, David Miller in particular. So this study was very simple. We took patients with multiple sclerosis and asked a simple question: Would stem cells from the bone marrow be protective of their nerves? So what we did was we took this bone marrow, grew up the stem cells in the lab, and then injected them back into the vein. I'm making this sound really simple. It took five years off a lot of people, okay? And it put gray hair on me and caused all kinds of issues. But conceptually, it's essentially simple. So we've given them into the vein, right? So in order to measure whether this was successful or not, we measured the optic nerve as our outcome measure. And that's a good thing to measure in M.S., because patients with M.S. sadly suffer with problems with vision -- loss of vision, unclear vision. And so we measured the size of the optic nerve using the scans with David Miller three times -- 12 months, six months, and before the infusion -- and you can see the gently declining red line. And that's telling you that the optic nerve is shrinking, which makes sense, because their nerves are dying. We then gave the stem cell infusion and repeated the measurement twice -- three months and six months -- and to our surprise, almost, the line's gone up. That suggests that the intervention has been protective. I don't think myself that what's happened is that those stem cells have made new myelin or new nerves. What I think they've done is they've promoted the endogenous stem cells, or precursor cells, to do their job, wake up, lay down new myelin. So this is a proof of concept. I'm very excited about that. So I just want to end with the theme I began on, which was regeneration and hope. So here I've asked John what his hopes are for the future. John: I would hope that sometime in the future through the research that you people are doing, we can come up with a cure so that people like me can lead a normal life. SC: I mean, that speaks volumes. But I'd like to close by first of all thanking John -- thanking John for allowing me to share his insights and these clips with you all. But I'd also like to add to John and to others that my own view is, I'm hopeful for the future. I do believe that the disruptive technologies like stem cells that I've tried to explain to you do offer very real hope. And I do think that the day that we might be able to repair the damaged brain is sooner than we think. Thank you. (Applause)
es encontrar vías que puedan estimular y activar esas células madre que ya están en el cerebro para reaccionar y responder apropiadamente al daño y repararlo. Ese será el futuro. Habrá medicamentos que harán eso. Pero la otra vía es lanzarse en paracaídas dentro de las células, trasplantarlas, para reemplazar células moribundas o perdidas, incluso en el cerebro. Y quiero hablarles ahora de un experimento, es un ensayo clínico que hicimos, y que se completó recientemente junto con colegas en UCL, David Miller en particular. Este estudio fue muy sencillo. Tomamos pacientes con esclerosis múltiple y nos planteamos una simple pregunta: ¿Protegerían las células madre de la médula ósea a sus nervios? Lo que hicimos fue que tomamos la médula ósea, desarrollamos las células madre en el laboratorio, y las inyectamos de nuevo en la vena. Estoy tratando de que suene muy sencillo. Pero le tomó 5 años a mucha gente, ¿está bien? Me sacó las canas y causó todo tipo de problemas. Sin embargo, conceptualmente es un experimento esencialmente simple. Entonces las hemos puesto en la vena, ¿verdad? Con el objetivo de comprobar si fue exitoso o no, tomamos el nervio óptico como nuestra medida de resultado. Esa es una buena manera para comprobar el avance de la esclerosis múltiple, porque lamentablemente los pacientes sufren de problemas de visión: pérdida de visión, visión borrosa. Y así, comprobamos el tamaño del nervio óptico usando los escáneres con David Miller tres veces --a los doce meses, a los seis meses, y antes de la inyección-- y pueden ver la línea roja descender ligeramente. Eso está diciéndonos que el nervio óptico se está reduciendo, lo que tiene sentido porque los nervios están muriendo. Entonces pusimos la inyección de células madre y repetimos la medición dos veces --a los tres meses y a los seis meses-- y casi para nuestra sorpresa, la línea subió. Eso sugiere que la intervención ha sido protectora. No creo que lo que pasó es que esas células madre hubieran creado nueva mielina o nuevos nervios. Lo que pienso que han hecho es que han estimulado las células madre endógenas o las células precursoras, para que hagan su trabajo: despertar, generar nueva mielina. Esta es una prueba de concepto. Y estoy muy emocionado con eso. Entonces quiero terminar con el tema con el que empecé, que fue regeneración y esperanza. De ese modo, le he preguntado a John cuáles son sus expectativas para el futuro. John: Esperaría que en el futuro, a través de la investigación que ustedes están haciendo, podamos obtener una cura, para que la gente como yo pueda llevar una vida normal. Eso lo dice todo. Me gustaría terminar agradeciendo a John en primer lugar, gracias a John por permitirme compartir sus ideas y estos cortos con ustedes. Pero también me gustaría decir a John y a los demás que mi punto de vista es: tengo esperanzas en el futuro. Creo que las tecnologías disruptivas, como las de las células madre que he tratado de explicarles hoy, ofrecen la verdadera esperanza. Y pienso que el día en que podamos ser capaces de reparar los cerebros lesionados está más cerca de lo que pensamos. Gracias. (Aplausos)